A Guide to the Papers of the Ivy Creek Foundation, 1916-1988
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Ivy Creek Foundation, 1916-1988
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10770
This collection consists of ca. 150 items (1 Hollinger box).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were loaned to the Library by the Ivy Creek Foundation of Charlottesville, Virginia, through Elizabeth Murray, Co-ordinator, on July 11, 1988.
Biographical/Historical Information
During the Reconstruction period of Virginia history, Hugh Carr (1843-1914), probably a freed slave, and his wife, Texie Mae Hawkins (? - 1899) began the long process of purchasing various tracts of land that eventually made up the 160 acre model farm along Ivy Creek known as "River View." When Hugh Carr died in 1914, his daughter, Mary Carr, a teacher in Charlottesville, and later principal of the Albemarle Training School, inherited a sixth of the farm. When Mary Carr married Conley Greer, an Albemarle County Agricultural Agent, in 1916, they began to purchase the other five shares of the farm from Mary's sisters.
After the death of Mrs. Greer, the farm was put up for sale and was in danger of becoming one of Charlottesville's newest subdivisions. Elizabeth Conant, a biology teacher at the University of Virginia, realized that the land was ideal for a nature preserve. She contacted the Nature Conservancy who bought the farm and held it until the City of Charlottesville and Albemarle County were able to buy the land. The Ivy Creek Foundation was incorporated on May 23, 1979, and the future management of the land lies with them. Paul Saunier, former University of Virginia administrator, was the first president of the Foundation. For further information about Mary Carr Greer and the Carr family see the Carr Family Papers (# 10, 176, -a-f) in Special Collections, Manuscript Division.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of the Ivy Creek Foundation of Albemarle County and Charlottesville, Virginia, consists of ca. 150 items (1 Hollinger box), 1916-1954, 1966-1988, and n.d., and contains material pertaining to the acquisition of the property for the Ivy Creek Natural Area (ICNA), begun in 1975 by the intervention of the Nature Conservancy, and the formation of the Ivy Creek Foundation in 1979 to administer the area.
This material includes two letters from Benjamin Whitten and T.C. Ritchie; legal and financial papers of Mary Carr Greer (1884-1973) and her husband, Conley Greer (? -1956), a local black family who ran a model farm named "River View" in the Ivy Creek area; newsclippings and articles about the formation of the ICNA and the work of its volunteers; research notes concerning the history of the Carr family and the transfers of title of the Carr property; notebooks entitled "ICNA History and Heritage" compiled by Price Smith in 1985, and the "Rann Preserve" kept by Elizabeth Conant; photographs of the ICNA, both aerial and ground level (including one oversize folder of ICNA photographs); copies of photographs of the Carr family; and a research paper entitled "Ivy Creek Natural Area. A Local Conservation Case Study" written by Patricia Farrell which explains how a local group concerned about conservation was able to purchase and administer the ICNA for the good of the whole Albemarle-Charlottesville area.
Also present are copies of documents showing the various steps in the acquisition of the Ivy Creek property, first by the Nature Conservancy and then by the Ivy Creek Foundation. Also present is documentation of the original ownership of the land by the Carr-Greer family.
The present day Ivy Creek Natural Area, which borders the South Rivanna Reservoir of the City of Charlottesville and consists of 215 acres of forest, field, and stream, was formed from several tracts of land. These include: 1) the original tract from the Mary Carr Greer Estate of eighty acres in 1975, 2) a thirty-eight acre tract from the City of Charlottesville in 1979 3) the Fleming tract of eighty acres in 1981 4) the Flamenco tract of sixteen acres in 1981 and 5) four tenths of an acre from Bedford Moore in 1981. The Greer property was named the Rann Preserve when purchased by the Nature Conservancy and renamed the Ivy Creek Natural Area when purchased by the Ivy Creek Foundation.
Contents List
- Acquisition of the Ivy Creek Natural Area 1978-1986
  Selected Documents showing steps in the City/County acquisition of property
- Articles re the Ivy Creek Natural Area 1977-1988
- Federal Assistance Application from the Ivy Creek Natural Area Program Committee 1977-1978
- Historical Notes and a title search on the Carr land n.d.
- "ICNA History and Heritage" Notebook 1985
- "Ivy Creek Natural Area. A Local Conservation Case Study" by Patricia Farrell 1986
- Legal and Financial Papers of Conley Greer and the Greer family 1916-1932, 1954
- Letters from Benjamin Whitten and T.C. Ritchie 1984
- Newsclippings re the ICNA and Ivy Creek Foundation 1975-1987, n.d.
- Notebook kept by Elizabeth Conant and Susan Schmidt 1977, n.d.
- Notes of personal conversations about Ivy Creek history w/ Elizabeth Murray, Co-ordinator for the Ivy Creek Fd. 1984-1987
- Photographs of members of the Carr family n.d., Copies
- Photographs of the Ivy Creek Natural Area 1966-1976, n.d.
  see also oversize folder of photographs
- Piedmont Environmental Council Citation and Award 1981
- Rann Preserve File kept by Elizabeth Conant 1966-1976